A Finding Aid to the Moses Ros Papers, 1978-2012, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Moses Ros papers
1978-2012
Archives of American Art
Ros, Moses, 1958-
AAA.rosmose
Archival Resource Key
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of Dominican American installation artist Moses Ros measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1978 to 2012. The collection is comprised of files for several New York City Housing Authority commissions, as well as architecture, sculpture, and mural projects; professional files for Dominican York Proyecto GRAFICA, MUD/BONE Print Studio, and a New York American Institute of Architects residency; printed materials; and artwork that includes doodles, sketches, mock ups, and a paper and feather mask.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated in 2016 by Moses Ros.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Biographical / Historical
Moses Ros (1958- ), also known as Moses Ros-Suárez, is a Dominican American installation artist in Bronx, New York. He was born in New York City to Dominican born parents. Ros received a bachelor's degree in architecture from Pratt Institute and is a licensed architect in the state of New York. He incorporates his knowledge of architecture into his numerous sculptural designs for community centers, daycare facilities, and other public spaces. He has completed sculpture, design, and mural commissions for the New York City Housing Authority, Bronx Council on the Arts, the Department of Cultural Affairs, and the Metropolitan Transit Authority. Ros has also been active with collaborative artist groups such as Dominican York Proyecto GRAFICA and MUD/Bone Print Studio.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Dominican American installation artist Moses Ros measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1978 to 2012. The collection is comprised of files for several New York City Housing Authority commissions, as well as architecture, sculpture, and mural projects; professional files for Dominican York Proyecto GRAFICA, MUD/BONE Print Studio, and a New York American Institute of Architects residency; printed materials; and artwork that includes doodles, sketches, mock ups, and a paper and feather mask.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as four series.
Series 1: Commission and Project Files, circa 2000 (Boxes 1, 4, OV 5; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Professional Files, 1997-2012 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Printed Materials, 1978-2012 (Boxes 1, 4, OV 6; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Artwork, circa 2000 (Boxes 1-4, OV 6; 1.0 linear feet)
Artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Installations (Art); Latino and Latin American artists; Dominican American artists
- Commission and Project Files, circa 2000; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1, 4, OV 5
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence, sketches, progress reports, photographs, agreements, invoices and receipts, and other documents relating to commissions for the New York City Housing Authority and Metropolitan Transit Authority. Also included are project files for paintings, sculptures, artist books, murals, and an exhibition for the Longwood Arts Project.
  - General, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - General, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Artist Books, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bubbles of Dreams, Washington Heights Daycare Center - Relief Sculptures, circa 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Casita Paintings, 2001-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cheery People, Atlantic Terminal Houses, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cheery People, Atlantic Terminal Houses, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Chocolate Kisses", circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Davidson Houses - Benches, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Plans for the benches include a version incorporating Ros's Myles Davis sculpture.
  - Freedom, DeHostos Community Center - Mural, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Freedom, DeHostos Community Center - Mural, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Fulton Street Transit Center Design, Application, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mi Casita, Williamsburg Daycare Center, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mitchel Houses Community Center, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Moject Calendar, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mural Project 1, Unidentified, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mural Project 1, Unidentified, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mural Project 2, Unidentified, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mural Project 2, Unidentified, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Murals, Urban Tape and Storefront, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Patriasana/Wholesomeland, Fordham Road Station - Glass, circa 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Projects, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes photographs of Freedom, Mi Casita, and unidentified projects.
  - "Physical Place, Virtual Space," Exhibition for Longwood Arts Project, 1998-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sculptures, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
    Includes giant print, head, poet, and various other sculpture projects.
  - Sculptures, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - St. Nicholas Houses Community Center, Mural, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Street Tree Time Capsules, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Taínovivo, Hostos Center for the Arts and Culture - Mobile, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Taínovivo, Hostos Center for the Arts and Culture - Mobile, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Throgg's Neck Houses Community Center, Process Photographs, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-32)
  - York College Childcare Center, 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - York College Childcare Center, 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
- Professional Files, 1997-2012; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Professional files document Ros's activities outside of his commission and project work. Meeting notes and agendas, correspondence, contracts, guidelines, and printed materials are included in files for the artist groups Dominican York Proyecto GRAFICA and MUD/BONE Print Studio. Additionally, a notebook and other material for a business course, information regarding a residency with the New York American Institute of Architects, receipts, and research material are also in the series.
  - Dominican York Proyecto GRAFICA, 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Make Your Art Your Business," Course Material, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - MUD/BONE Print Studio, 2006-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - New York American Institute of Architects, Residency, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Receipts, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Research Material, circa 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes an artist's services list, article on Alexander Calder, a paper on Leonardo Da Vinci, and information on mural and outdoor sculpture materials and techniques.
- Printed Materials, 1978-2012; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1, 4, OV 6
  Printed materials consist of art reproductions, booklets, clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, newsletters, and posters regarding Ros and his artwork, public artwork in New York City, and arts organizations.
  - Art Reproductions, 1978-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Booklets, circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Brochures, 1988-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, Newspaper, 2002-2012; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1994-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
    Includes a mock up of the Empowerment exhibition catalog.
  - Newsletters, 2000-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Posters, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Artwork, circa 2000; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 1-4, OV 6
  Doodles interspersed with notes, sketches for various projects, a paper and feather mask, and mock ups that include panels covered with paint or colored paper are in artwork.
  - Doodles, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
  - Doodles, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Doodles, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Mask, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Mask is constructed from colored paper and feathers.
  - Mock Ups, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes a wooden rod, paper circle, mosaic sample, and a small animal sculpture.
  - Mock Ups, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    Includes rectangular panels covered with drawings and colored paper.
  - Mock Ups, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
    Includes painted gold rectangular panels and a "Trabajos Armados" banner.
  - Sketches, circa 1980-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    Some sketches are photocopies from a sketchbook.
  - Sketches, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)